<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An assize-sermon preach'd before Judge Twisselton and Serj. Bernard at Carlisle September the 10th, ann. 1660 and now publish'd and recommended to the magistrates of the nation, as a means by God's blessing to quicken them to a serious pursuit of the honourable and truly religious design, for the reformation of manners, which is now on foot, and countenanced by the nobility, bishop's and judges, in the late account of the societies for the reformation of manner's and applauded by the serious and religious men of all perswasions / by R. Gilpin ...</title>
            <author>Gilpin, Richard, 1625-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42779</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5869</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13693301</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13693301</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101413</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42779)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101413)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 844:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An assize-sermon preach'd before Judge Twisselton and Serj. Bernard at Carlisle September the 10th, ann. 1660 and now publish'd and recommended to the magistrates of the nation, as a means by God's blessing to quicken them to a serious pursuit of the honourable and truly religious design, for the reformation of manners, which is now on foot, and countenanced by the nobility, bishop's and judges, in the late account of the societies for the reformation of manner's and applauded by the serious and religious men of all perswasions / by R. Gilpin ...</title>
                  <author>Gilpin, Richard, 1625-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ... and Sarah Burton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms II, 12 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101413:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101413:1"/>
            <p>AN ASSIZE-SERMON Preach'd before Judge <hi>Twiſſelton</hi> and Serj. <hi>Bernard</hi> AT CARLISLE <hi>September</hi> the 10th <hi>Ann.</hi> 1660.</p>
            <p>AND Now Publiſh'd and Recommended to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of the Nation, as a Means by God's Bleſſing to quicken them to a ſerious Purſuit of the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and truly Religious Deſign, for the Reformation of Manners, which is now on foot, and Countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Nobility, Biſhop's, and Judges, in the late Account of the Societies for the Reformation of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's, and applauded by the Serious and Religious Men of all Perſwaſions.</p>
            <p>By <hi>R. GILPIN,</hi> Now Miniſter of the GOSPEL in <hi>NEWCASTLE</hi> upon <hi>TYNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho Parkhurſt,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and Three <hi>Crowns</hi> near <hi>Mercers-Chapple;</hi> and <hi>Sarah Burton,</hi> Bookſeller at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101413:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101413:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Worſhipful, and WORSHIPFUL
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> WILLIAM BLACKETT <hi>Baronet, Mayor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> ROBERT SHAFTOE <hi>Recorder.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <head>
                           <hi>ALDERMEN of the Town and County of</hi> NEWCASTLE.</head>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sir</hi> RALPH CARR <hi>Kt.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>TIMOTHY ROBSON <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>NICHOLAS FENWICK <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>WILLIAM AUBONY <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>WILLIAM CARR <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>MATTHEW WHITE <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>THOMAS WASS <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>JOSEPH ATKINSON <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>GEORGE WHINFIELD <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>ROBERT EDEN <hi>Eſq;</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>EDWARD HARRISON <hi>Eſq; Sheriff.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Printing of the following Sermon, now al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Forty Years after it was Preached, needs a longer Apology, than at preſent either my Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure will allow, or others perhaps will have Patience to read: To ſave therefore my ſelf and others from a
<pb facs="tcp:101413:3"/>needleſs Trouble, I ſhall only tell you, That theſe <hi>Notes</hi> were bury'd among my Papers, and out of Mind, but upon a particular Occaſion they came to Hand. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon a ſhort view of them, I conceiv'd they might be of ſome uſe to quicken Magiſtrates in that Noble and Important Duty, of the <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Manners,</hi> which of late hath been publickly counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced and own'd by many perſons of great Name, <hi>Noblemen, Biſhop's,</hi> and <hi>Judges.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Author of the Account of the <hi>Societies</hi> for <hi>Reformation,</hi> hath with a commendable Zeal, and many unanſwerable Arguments, urg'd this Religious Deſign upon all ſorts of Men; and there ſeems not to be any neceſſity to add any thing to that which is ſo excellently done already; yet ſuch is the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Human <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, that even where the Conviction of Reaſon is ſo clear and full, as makes new Arguments uſeleſs, yet through the Weakneſs either of Memory, or want of due Impreſſion, we are apt to let them ſlip. In this Caſe where Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments are uſeleſs, a Remembrancer may be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
            <p>This Sermon was Preach'd at a Critical Time, as appears by its date; to ſpeak Boldly upon ſuch a Subject at that time, ſeem'd ſo hazardous, that thoſe that heard it, expected that I ſhould meet
<pb facs="tcp:101413:3"/>with ſome Effects of the Judges angry Reſentments; but ſuch was their Conſcientious regard to the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that was ſpoken, and ſuch were their Convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Truth and Weight of it, that contrary to all expectation, they publickly recommended the <hi>Sermon</hi> to the Conſideration of the <hi>Grand-Jury,</hi> and in private alſo gave me their Hearty thanks.</p>
            <p>The main Drift and Deſign of the <hi>Sermon</hi> is, to Excite Magiſtrates to countenance the Practice of our Holy Religion, and to puniſh Vice and Decauchery: Seeing then this is the thing that is now expected from Magiſtrates, as their Duty which they owe to God, and to the Safety and well government of the Country; why may not this be uſeful to them by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in remembrance.</p>
            <p>Many of the Reverend Pious <hi>Clergy</hi> of both De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominations, have preach'd and printed <hi>Sermons</hi> for the promoting of a <hi>Reformation;</hi> this though preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long before, yet is not printed ſo much out of due Time, but that it may come in the Rear.</p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe I humbly offer to the ſerious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Magiſtrates of the Nation, and more particularly to you, whoſe Names are prefix'd to theſe Papers (as the preſent Magiſtrates of the Famous Town and County of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> upon <hi>Tyne,</hi> where I
<pb facs="tcp:101413:4"/>have lived many Years,) partly as a Teſtimony of my Reſpect to your ſelves, which I am oblig'd to, for your civil Reſpects to me, and partly as a Teſtimony of my beſt Wiſhes to the whole Corporation, for their Spiritual and Temporal Proſperity, but chiefly to give you my Thanks publickly for what you have already done, in prohibiting Tipling in Publick-houſes on the <hi>Lord's-day:</hi> 'Tis a good Beginning, and you have honour'd your ſelves ſo much by it, that Judge <hi>Powell</hi> in his Charge at your laſt <hi>Aſſize,</hi> thought fit to take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honour'd Gentlemen!</hi> Give me leave to tell you, that a <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Manners,</hi> is a truly Religious and Noble <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, you will hereby ſhew that you take God's part, and fight againſt the Devil's Kingdom: You may expect that the Prince of Darkneſs will ſtir up his Inſtruments againſt you, but the Battle is the Lord's, and if you faithfully plead his Cauſe, and put due ſhame and diſgrace impartially upon Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery and Vice, he will ſtand by you, and own you, and your Names will be Honourable among all good Men.</p>
            <p>Be ſtrong therefore, and quit your ſelves like Men and good Chriſtians, you have many conſiderable Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages on your ſide, beſides the Divine aſſiſtance and protection which is the Chief; you have not only
<pb facs="tcp:101413:4"/>the Advantage of Law, but the Example and Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement of the moſt conſiderable Perſons of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; you may promiſe your ſelves the hearty Concurrence of all the Serious Religious <hi>Clergy,</hi> whoſe Office it is by all means to Promote the Honour of God, to whoſe Service they have devoted themſelves, and you may expect to ſee the Bleſſed Effects of your Religious Endeavours, to your great Comfort and Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add this, The hearty Agreement and Concurrence of Men of different Perſwaſions in other Points relating to Religion, in promoting of the Practice of ſerious Piety, and in putting a Diſgrace upon Vice, is the beſt Means that was ever yet offer'd for the Agreement of all our Differences in other Matters; this is what all good Men would be glad to ſee: But as the Caſe ſtands, there is little Ground to hope or expect it, and the great Thing that ſtands in the way, is the Perjudice which is deeply radicated in the Minds of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Parties, occaſion'd by mutual Reproaches, Revitings, and Paſſion, that our angry Contentions have produc'd againſt one another: This Prejudice is now become ſo invincible, that except this holy Oil of Brotherly Concord in this Matter do ſoften it, and beget a love in Men ſeriouſly Religious, the Fire will not be extinguiſhed: We are already agreed in
<pb facs="tcp:101413:5"/>the Doctrinal Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and if we were as heartily agreed too in the End of all True Religion, as in the Principles, a farther Progreſs would be more feaſible: This might be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to beget a brotherly Love to one another, and then we would more calmly hear, and more clearly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand our mutual Reaſonings about the remaining Differences, which would either incline us to Condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion for Peace ſake, or enable us to bear with one another, ſo that all might <hi>keep the unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace.</hi> That ſuch Effects may be produc'd ſhall be the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Humble Servant <hi>R. GILPIN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101413:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM II. v. xij.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Kiſs the Son leſt he be angry, and ye periſh from the way, when his wrath is kindled but a little, bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THIS <hi>Pſalm</hi> is a Prophetick Diſcourſe of the Kingdom of Chriſt, ſhewing what ſhould happen to it, and what ſhould happen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of it, in all Ages. Herein is ſet down;
<list>
                  <item>1. The Oppoſition that is made againſt Chriſt's King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</item>
                  <item>2. The Vanity of that Oppoſition.</item>
                  <item>3. The Application of both.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Oppoſition that Chriſt's Kingdom ſhould meet withal is the greateſt that may be, and that in theſe three Reſpects, 1. It is univerſal, made by all Sorts of People, not only by the common Rout (whoſe Perſons ordinarily diſgrace their Cauſe, and who (like the wild Aſs) do car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry their Bow in their Heels, or (<hi>Parthian</hi> like) ſhoot their Arrows backwards): But King's and Ruler's alſo appear in in this Oppoſition, who however unworthy, and ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful they are in their Attempt to Juſtle that God out of all, that takes them up into his Throne (as that of <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. v. 5. is expounded of <hi>Conſtantine</hi>) yet are they moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prevail. 2. The greatneſs of this Oppoſition to the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101413:6"/>Kingdom of Chriſt appears alſo, in that they who are inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in it, do make it their Buſineſs to drive it up to the greateſt height, For 1. They ſummon up their whole ſtrength to accompliſh it: And 2. The King's of the Earth themſelves back this their ſtrength with Policy and Counſel, <hi>The Ruler's take counſel together,</hi> v. 2. And not only ſo, but 3. They harden themſelves in theſe their Ways with firm Reſolutions, <hi>they ſet themſelves,</hi> &amp;c. v. 2. and 4. They incourage themſelves therein with hopeful Imaginations, <hi>The People imagine a vain thing</hi> v. 1, and 5. They whet their courage and reſolutions with Rage, <hi>The Heathen rage,</hi> &amp;c. v. 1. 3. The greatneſs of this Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is ſuch, that it is accompany'd with the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Demands imaginable, no leſs than this will ſerve; That God muſt part with his Soveraignty, lay down his Scepter, repeal his Laws, and ſuffer them to live as they liſt v. 3. <hi>Let us break their bands aſunder, and caſt away their cords from us.</hi> This was the Oppoſition, now follows.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Vanity of this Oppoſition made againſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt: Which appears in theſe Four things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In its unlikelineſs, v. 4. <hi>God ſits in Heaven,</hi> above their reach, beholding their undertakings as ridiculous, he laughs at their vain Attempts, as you would do at Worms that ſhould endeavour to ſtorm Caſtles, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter Armies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. The Vanity of theſe Men's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings is made evident farther in the vexatiouſneſs of the diſappointment they meet withal in the Proſecution of theſe Attempts, God will fret and vex them, by carrying on all his Deſigns, maugre the utmoſt of their Oppoſition, v. 5, 6. He will <hi>vex</hi> them with this,—<hi>Yet have I ſet my King upon my holy hill.</hi> 3. The abſolute impoſſibility of Succeſs, ſhews the Vanity of the undertaken Oppoſition; for, here is no leſs againſt them, than 1. An irrevocable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101413:6"/>Decree, v. 7. <hi>A decree already declar'd,</hi> and Promulgated, from which God cannot recede in point of honour; and 2. There is Chriſt's Merit and Interceſſion againſt them, which God will not diſappoint, v. 7. <hi>Thou art my Son.</hi> v. 8. <hi>Ask of me and I will give,</hi> &amp;c. which ſhews 3. That there is alſo againſt them, God's Covenant with Chriſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that undertaking, wherein he had ingaged himſelf to ſee the Oppoſition brought to nought, <hi>I will give,</hi> &amp;c. v. 8. ſo that 4. The Vanity of their Attempt appears from the ſpeedy, certain, and irrecoverable Ruin of the Attempters: v. 9. <hi>Thou ſhalt break him with a rod of Iron, thou ſhalt daſh them in pieces like a Potters Veſſel.</hi> A Potters Veſſel muſt needs break with a ſtroke eſpecially of an Iron rod, and being broke its thenceforth uſeleſs; and ſuch is the Caſe of theſe vain Oppoſers of Chriſt's Kingdom.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Application of theſe two (this Oppoſition and the Vanity of it), is directed only to King's and Ruler's, v. 10. <hi>Be wiſe now therefore O ye King's,</hi> &amp;c. not that others are unconcerned in it, but becauſe 1. They are not ſo eaſily perſwaded to deſiſt from ſo fooliſh an underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as the Vulgar are, as having ſtronger Temptations and Judgments to proſecute this Oppoſition, than others have: Being uſually Jealous of Chriſt's Kingdom as of that, that does too much ſtreighten and limit them in their Pleaſures, abridge them of the abſoluteneſs of their Authority, eclipſe their Honours, and vex them with Reproofs, and ſearching Convictions. 2. It is directed to them becauſe they do more dangerouſly oppoſe and reſiſt, both in reſpect of themſelves and others; for, their Perſonal Offences in this kind may become National Sins, and conſequently may occaſion National Puniſhments. 3. This Application is eſpecially directed to King's and Ruler's, becauſe their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Example (if they yield), hath a great Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:101413:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:101413:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:101413:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101413:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:101413:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101413:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101413:10"/>upon others to bring them alſo under Chriſt's yoke. The Duty that is here preſſed upon them is, 1. General, to ſtir them up to Wiſdom, and Serious Conſideration, v. 10. and 2. more Special, conſidering them in their double Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of being private and publick Perſons, 1. as Private Men that have precious Souls to take care for, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly they are advis'd to ſtrictneſs and ſincerity of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, v. 11. <hi>Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice with tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:</hi> I thus interpret it, becauſe theſe are Duties that are incumbent upon Chriſtians as Chriſtians; and 2. under a publick Capacity, or as they are Magiſtrates, they are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to have a care of others in the management of their Office, and ſo they are advis'd to own and advance Chriſt's Government and Kingdom, v. 12. <hi>Kiſs the Son,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Text contains two Parts, 1. The Duty: and 2. The Motives to it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Duty which is contain'd in theſe Words, <hi>Kiſs the Son;</hi> a Kiſs is a publick Symbol and Teſtification 1. of Love, as the uſe of the greateſt Part of the World ſhews; 2. of Subjection, as appears by the Phraſes of kiſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Baal,</hi> and kiſſing the <hi>Calves.</hi> Kiſs the Son, that is, teſtify your Love and Subjection by ſubmitting to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and promoting his Honour and Authority, in all your Offices.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Motives to this Duty are, 1. his Diſpleaſure, if you refuſe, <hi>Kiſs the Son leaſt he be angry.</hi> 2. You are ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if he be diſpleas'd: <hi>If he be angry you periſh.</hi> 3. The ſuddenneſs, and unexpectedneſs of the overthrow, <hi>while you are in the way,</hi> in the height of your purſuit and hopes. 4. The eaſineſs of the diſpatch, a little wrath will effect your overthrow. <hi>When his wrath is kindled but a little,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101413:10"/>5. The happineſs of Submiſſion, <hi>Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe words I ſhall propound one Doctrine which is this. That,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> Magiſtrates owe ſuch Homage and Subjection to Chriſt, that in all their Government, they muſt advance his Kingdom, upon pain of his Diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>In the Explication of this Doctrine I ſhall ſhew,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Magiſtrates Debt, and</item>
                  <item>2. Their Duty.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt then,</hi> They owe Homage to Chriſt, that is their Debt, 1. becauſe he is higher than they, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47. <hi>v.</hi> 2. <hi>He is a great King, the only Potentate, King of King's, and Lord of Lord's,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. v. 15. <hi>The eternal, immortal, inviſible King,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. v. 17. <hi>The univerſal King of all the Earth,</hi> Pſal. 47. v. 7. <hi>he hath prepared his throne in the heavens, his Kingdom ruleth over all,</hi> Pſal. 103. v. 19. The greateſt Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler upon Earth, in all his higheſt and mightieſt Titles and Power, is but a glittering guilded Potſherd; he is but illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, mighty, moſt excellent, honourable Duſt and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, take the higheſt Title the Scripture affords, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. <hi>v.</hi> 1. where they are all called God's, yet they are but God's Metaphorical, either analogically having ſome ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of God in their height above others, as high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Cedars are call'd God's Mountains and Cedars; or repreſentatively, becauſe they ſit in his Throne, and do (as it were) repreſent his Perſon; for they are notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101413:11"/>ſuch God's as are but Men, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. <hi>v.</hi> 7. and when they are dead, their Aſhes ſhall carry no more Prints of Honour than the Beggars that embraces the Dunghil, nor ſhall be diſtinguiſh'd from common Duſt. And if ſome aſpired higher, as <hi>Caligula, Domitian,</hi> &amp;c. who arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated Divine Honours to themſelves, yet God diſcover'd their folly, by making good that threatning, <hi>They ſhall fall like one of the Princes,</hi> or as <hi>Illyricus</hi> expounds it, like thoſe <hi>Tyrants that periſh in their Cruelties:</hi> That dye as <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8th like a Dog, and have <hi>Jehojakim</hi>'s Burial, the <hi>burial of an Aſs.</hi> If in the World petty King's ſhew Homage to the more Potent, as it was in the <hi>Heptarchy</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and under the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Graecian</hi> Conquerours, much more then do the greateſt Rulers owe Homage to God, upon account of his Greatneſs; <hi>have you an Arm like God, or can you Thunder with a Voice like his,</hi> if not, then <hi>bring pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents to him,</hi> Pſal. 72. v. 9, 10. <hi>They that dwell in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs ſhall bow before him: The King's of</hi> Tarſhiſh, <hi>and of the Iſles ſhall bring Preſents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Second</hi> reaſon to Prove that even King's and Ruler's owe Homage to Chriſt is, Becauſe all their Authority is derived from him: Their Authority is derivative theſe two ways. 1. <hi>In Conſtitutione Regiminis,</hi> and 2. <hi>Inſtitutione &amp; deſignatione perſonarum.</hi> 1. In the Conſtitution of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment it ſelf: Dominion and Rule is Chriſt's appointment, even in the State of Innocency, as <hi>Parens</hi> obſerves, God gave Man Power over himſelf (by free Will) and over the Creatures, and his Family too: Which (though ſome think that the State of Innocency and Magiſtracy are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent yet) carries ſome reſemblance at leaſt of Magiſtracy; however ſince their Fall, as God appointed Sun and Stars to rule Day and Night, ſo hath he appointed Magiſtracy (as Stars in their Courſes) as a means of Order in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101413:11"/>Hence it is call'd <hi>God's Ordinance,</hi> in which Word there is a ſpecial Emphaſis (it is <hi>Tolet</hi>'s obſervation), they are not of God as <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Famine</hi> are ſaid to be of his Appointment, but they are more eſpecially or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Command and Promiſe: 2. The Authority of Rulers is derivative too in <hi>deſignatione Perſonae:</hi> Thus he appointed <hi>Saul,</hi> found out <hi>David,</hi> and choos'd <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> &amp;c. Yea in unjuſt Uſurpations, though the Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of attaining and managing be not <hi>à Deo approbante,</hi> having not the Allowance of his <hi>preceptive Will:</hi> Yet they are <hi>à Deo permittente,</hi> and according to <hi>his Will of Purpoſe:</hi> The <hi>Powers that are,</hi> Rom. 13. (which points at <hi>Nero,</hi> for the Abſtract cannot conſiſt without the Concrete), <hi>are ordain'd of God.</hi> Nature teacheth all Creatures a thankful Reſpect to them from whom they had their Being; the Rivers pay a conſtant Tribute to the Sea, whence they all come, much more then ſhould Magiſtrates own that God that gave them as well their Natural Beings (for they are the Work of his Hands as Men), as alſo their Political Beings, for they are the <hi>Children of the moſt high</hi> as Magiſtrates, ſuch a tributary was <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 7. v. 18, to 22.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Third</hi> argument that ſhews that King's and Ruler's ought to be Chriſt's Homagers is, That as their Power is borrow'd, ſo alſo it is <hi>ad Placitum</hi> (not abſolute and independent), and that two ways. 1. In regard of their Rules, Laws, and Limits, which God hath fix'd for their direction, he is the ſupreme Lawgiver, and they muſt take the Law from his Mouth, in the Eſſentials of Piety and Juſtice: He hath given them poſitive Commands, which they are not to Tranſgreſs; In Circumſtantials, and particular Emergencies, which although he hath left un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determin'd, yet even there he hath given general Rules
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101413:12"/>of Order, Decency, Edification, and <hi>Salus Populi</hi> to walk by in their determinations of Things, <hi>ad hic &amp; nunc:</hi> 2. They are dependent on his Pleaſure for the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation of the Power in their Perſons, <hi>he taketh down one, and ſetteth up another,</hi> he can cut off the Spirit of Princes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76. v. 12. and can raiſe up the <hi>poor out of the mire,</hi> and the <hi>needy from the dunghil to ſet him with Princes,</hi> Pſal. 113. v. 7, 8. Pope <hi>Coeleſtin</hi> crown'd the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> with his Feet, and ſpurn'd off the Crown again, as an Emblematical boaſt of his Power, of making and unmaking King's; but though this was too much Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy for Man, yet it is one of the <hi>Jura Regalia</hi> of the King of Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> King's and Ruler's owe Homage to Chriſt, becauſe as their Authority depends on him, ſo it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Miniſterial in ſubordination to God's Ends and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; the Magiſtrate is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God, God's Agent and Servant, his <hi>Eſſe</hi> as a Magiſtrate is <hi>alterius eſſe,</hi> a Servant entruſted by his Lord, may have many encouraging Priviledges and Advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for himſelf, yet the great End of his Employment and Advancement, is his Maſters ſervice and profit; the Honour and Power of Ruler's are not terminated, neither wholly, nor chiefly upon their own Perſons, as if God deſign'd only the gratifying of ſome few Men above the common Rank of Mankind, giving theſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities for their Perſon's ſakes, only to make them Great: No! His main End is, the Service and Fruit that is expected from them both to God and Man, and the Dignity is affix'd to the Perſon, as an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to, and a neceſſary Means of doing that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: They are but God's creatures and ſubſtitutes, for affecting his Will in the Government of his Church in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101413:12"/>the World; to them therefore I may apply that of the Apoſtle, <hi>Ye are not your own,</hi> your Places and Offices are not given, but with Reference to your Service; then give Homage to your Maſter whoſe you are, and for whoſe Ends you are employ'd; he is an unworthy Servant that grows Proud and Inſolent by his Maſter's bounty, and yet 'tis a common Fault, as appears by the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> Chap. II. v. 31. <hi>When God had been no barren Wilderneſs to them,</hi> but had given <hi>ſhowers of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings,</hi> they <hi>could wax wanton,</hi> and ſay, <hi>we are Lords, we will come no more unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That Magiſtrates owe Homage to God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in that this <hi>Depoſitum</hi> is given them in reference to an Account; and ſurely Homage is due, where Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts are unavoidable: <hi>Give an Account of thy Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> will be a terrible Voice to thoſe Servants, who (upon a conceit of the Lord's delay) inſtead of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Houſe in Order, have become the Maſter's of Miſ-rule, and have eaten and drunk with the Drunken: The Lord of that Servant will make him know that he hath not <hi>given to God, the things that are God's,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever pretence he might make of <hi>giving to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Sometimes Perſonal Obligations from God calls for Homage, as of this Nature are the Perſonal Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of ſome for ſuch an Imployment, and of this Nature too is the very <hi>Means</hi> and <hi>Manner</hi> of Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in ſome others; when God by a ſtrong Hand, and (as it were) from the Dead ſets them upon the Throne. <hi>Who am I</hi> ſaith <hi>David,</hi> 2 Sam. 7.18. <hi>and what is my Houſe that thou haſt brought me hitherto?</hi> A Spirit of Magiſtracy may be an Obligation upon others, as it was in <hi>Saul,</hi> who had another Spirit given upon his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming of the Magiſtracy; ſo their Succeſs and Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101413:13"/>may oblige others, when they hold up the Pillars of a ſhaking Land as <hi>David</hi> did; and others again may be induc'd by the Eminency of their Service, as when they lay the Foundation of the Lord's Houſe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo bring out the Head-ſtone with ſhouting, as <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Zerubbable;</hi> or when they are Inſtruments of ſome ſignal Deliverance, as <hi>Gideon, Jephtha,</hi> &amp;c. or become a Means to Reform the People (over whom they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted) from their Wickedneſſes as <hi>Joſiah</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Thus much for Explication of the Magiſtrates <hi>Debt,</hi> we are now to take Notice of the Second Thing that offer'd it ſelf to our Conſideration from the Doctrine, and that is, the <hi>Duty</hi> incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon Magiſtrates, which is, to Advance the Kingdom of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> why Magiſtrates are thus bound to Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance Chriſt's Kingdom are theſe;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is God's Deſign all along to Advance the Kingdom of Chriſt, and to this End, 1. He hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven all Power into his Hand, Matth. 28.18. <hi>All Power is given unto me in heaven and in earth:</hi> John 13.3, <hi>Jeſus knowing that the Father had given all things into his Hands,</hi> &amp;c. God hath then committed all Judgment and Authority to Chriſt to execute it, John 5.22. <hi>The Father judgeth no Man, but hath committed all Judgment unto the Son,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 27. He hath given him Authority to execute Judgment alſo, becauſe he is the <hi>Son of Man, and for this end Chriſt both died and roſe again, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived, that he might be Lord both of the Dead and Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> Rom. 14.9. 2. Upon this Account alſo God hath promis'd to enlarge Chriſt's Territories, <hi>in the Hearts of a willing People in the Day's of his Power,</hi> even to the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101413:13"/>Heathen and uttermoſt Parts of the Earth, that all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Nations ſhould Serve him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. 3. Hence alſo he hath commanded all to Submit to him, he hath alſo a <hi>Name</hi> above every Name, Philip. 2.9. <hi>God alſo hath highly exalted him, and given him a Name which is above every Name.</hi> v. 10. <hi>That at the Name of Jeſus eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Knee ſhould bow:</hi> That is, that all ſhould expreſs their reverent Submiſſion and Obedience to him; <hi>bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Knee</hi> (being a Geſture of Reſpect) is put for all Acts of inward and outward Obedience: They that interpret it of the Geſture of bowing at the name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word <hi>Jeſus,</hi> do not only affix that to the Name, which is intended to the Perſon (for otherwiſe they ſhould bow at the Name <hi>Chriſt, Immanuel,</hi> &amp;c.) but alſo level the Place to a far lower Senſe, and would put much leſs Honour on Chriſt, than the Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. 4. For this End alſo (<hi>viz.</hi> the Advancement of the Kingdom of Chriſt), God hath ordain'd Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy, deſigning it for an eſpecial Means of advancing Chriſt's Kingdom, and therefore it is the Magiſtrates Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to concur and comply with this grand Deſign of God, in reference to the Advancement of the Kingdom of Chriſt. Which,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If Magiſtrates do not, they neglect the main Work and Buſineſs of their Places; for although it be queſtion'd whoſe Vicegerents they are, whether God's as Creatour, or Chriſt's as Mediatour, and though the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Magiſtrates Power in Eccleſiaſtical Matters be diſputed, while <hi>Eraſtus</hi> would give all to them, and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus</hi> take all from them; yet I ſay, however moſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Men agree, that the great End of Magiſtracy is the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Chriſt's Kingdom, even as it is the End of Miniſtry: And therefore <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (which is a general Name is attributed to both, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101413:14"/>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> having relation to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the precedent Verſe; ſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is a Title of Magiſtracy; True! Though Miniſters and Magiſtrates have the ſame End, yet they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in the Way of Proſecution; the Magiſtrates cannot <hi>eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere actus Eccleſiaſticos</hi> (as Preach the Word, Adminiſter the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) for that coſt <hi>Saul</hi> the loſs of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> a Leproſy; but yet he may <hi>Imperare &amp; cöercere,</hi> and therefore that Good for which he is a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, is not only <hi>Natural</hi> for the Preſervation of Life, <hi>Civil</hi> for the Preſervation of Eſtate, <hi>Moral</hi> to keep off Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances in Life and Manners; but alſo <hi>Spiritual</hi> for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Religion (as <hi>Paren</hi>'s well obſerves): And indeed this is one of the Ends of our Prayers for you, that you in your Stations may be ſerviceable in promoting Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for ſo you have it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. where Prayers and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſions are injoin'd for <hi>King's and all that are in Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable Life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty;</hi> and conſequently you come ſhort of the End of your Office, if you omit to take care for the Church of Chriſt; if you neglect this, you are but <hi>empty Vines, Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels wherein is no Pleaſure, ſounding Braſs and tinkling Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Your refuſal of this Care, is oppoſition and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt Chriſt, there is no nutrality between Chriſt and the Devil, betwixt Religion and Irreligion; Men in this Caſe muſt either be Friends or Enemies, Act for him or againſt him, for where the Duty is neceſſary (as it is here) the wilful neglect is Rebellion: In this Caſe that Proverb is True, Matth. 12.30. <hi>He that is not with me is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</hi> Not to be againſt Chriſt as a Teacher aſſerting Truth is to be for him: Mark 9.40. <hi>He that is not againſt us, is on our part:</hi> Not to be for him as a King warring againſt Satan's Kingdom, is to be againſt him.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:101413:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Conſider that if you be ſlow in promoting Chriſt's Cauſe, you contract the Guilt of other Men's Sins, and that two Ways; 1. <hi>Non prohibendo,</hi> for, <hi>Qui non prohibet cum poteſt jubet:</hi> And 2. You do it <hi>Exemplo,</hi> for if Magiſtrates be Supine and Careleſs, People will eaſily ſee it, and think their Example a warrantable Pattern for Imitation: <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Samaria</hi> were Royal Cities (where were the Thrones for Judgment) hence they were the <hi>Fountains of Iniquity</hi> to the Land, and the Sins of the Land charged upon them, Micah. 1.5. <hi>What is the tranſgreſſion of Jacob? Is it not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria? And what are the high places of Judah? Are they not Jeruſalem?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> If Magiſtrates advance not the Throne of Chriſt, they commonly prove Furious againſt it, and Plagues of God's People; if this proceed from a careleſs blockiſh Temper, then <hi>Judgment</hi> of it ſelf will degenerate into <hi>Gall,</hi> and the <hi>Fruit of Righteouſneſs</hi> into <hi>Hemlock.</hi> Juſtice like Water, purifies it ſelf by Motion, when it <hi>runs down like a ſtream;</hi> if it be a ſtanding Water it Corrupts, and <hi>Corruptio optimorum peſſima.</hi> If this neglect proceed from Enmity to Chriſt, then ſeeing they have the greateſt Advantages in their Hands to do Evil, they may <hi>eſtabliſh Wickedneſs by a Law:</hi> They <hi>can puſh with the horn, and tread down the Paſture with their feet,</hi> Ezek. 34.18. <hi>When the wicked beareth rule the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple mourn,</hi> Prov. 29.2. Or, if it proceed from Apoſtacy, then the <hi>revollers are profound to make ſlaughter,</hi> Hoſ. 5.2. And this happens not ſo much from the Churliſh and Cruel Diſpoſitions of Men, as from God's giving them up judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to Rage againſt his Ways, either as a Scourge to his People, or in order to their own Ruin: Hence 'tis noted, that the cruelleſt Perſecutions were ſet on foot by Emperours ſometimes of the beſt Parts and moſt civil Diſpoſitions, as <hi>Antoninus Philoſophus, Trajan, Severus, Decius,</hi> &amp;c. Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are for the moſt Part like the Prophet's Figs, either
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101413:15"/>very good, or very bad, they are the Heads of the People, and all Diſeaſes in the Head are Dangerous: So when the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſy appear'd in the Head deeper than the Skin, the party was pronounc'd utterly unclean.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> If Chriſtian Magiſtrates do not Advance the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, what do they more than Heathen Magiſtrates? Chriſt will have his Subjects to outſtrip the Heathen, as you may perceive by his arguing, Matth. 5. <hi>Do not even the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans ſo?</hi> Heathens have made Good Laws for Moral Hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and have been juſt in the Execution of them, as among the <hi>Athenians Solon,</hi> the <hi>Lacedaemonians Lycurgus.</hi> There were many Good Laws among the <hi>Romans,</hi> but of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaemonian</hi> Laws <hi>Eraſmus</hi> gives you this Account; <hi>Dixeris</hi> ſays he, ſpeaking of their Laws, <hi>Chriſtianos, ſi pro Lycurgo Chriſtum nacti fuiſſent Legiſlatorum.</hi> Nay you find farther, that even among the Heathens, the <hi>Decij</hi> and the <hi>Curtij,</hi> &amp;c. have devoted themſelves to Death for the Publick.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Seventh</hi> Reaſon why Magiſtrates ſhould ſet themſelves to Advance Chriſt's Kingdom is, becauſe People are deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated Good or Bad, from the goodneſs or badneſs of their Ruler's; for 1. The more noble Part gives the Denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a heap of Wheat and Chaff is call'd a heap of Wheat: And 2. it influenceth the reſt; I ſpeak of external Goodneſs of Profeſſion chiefly; though as a Means it may be extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to internal: If <hi>Jeroboam</hi> be wicked, the Ten Tribes are ſo: And to this purpoſe you have the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> telling you, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.26. That a Reſtauration of Good Ruler's (for it ſpeaks of the Qualifications not the <hi>Species</hi> of Ruler's <hi>v.</hi> 23.) makes a City of Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>I have now done with the Explanation of the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> my next Work is to apply it. And,</p>
            <p>Here I muſt firſt addreſs my ſelf to the Reverend Judges, and the Magiſtrates of this County, and becauſe the time will
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101413:15"/>not allow me to ſpeak to you ſeverally; I ſhall direct my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to you all at once, that as God hath lifted up your Heads above your Brethren, ſo you would ſtudy to Advance his Honour and Kingdom: <hi>Kiſs the Son:</hi> Give me leave in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to your Souls, and in diſcharge of my Duty (for ſurely I am not call'd either by God or Man to Complement with you) to be plain with you in a few Directions: And ſurely if you were in my ſtead, and heard God ſpeaking to you, <hi>Son of Man tell the Houſe of Iſrael their Sin, elſe their Blood will I require at thine Hand, lift up thy Voice like a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, ſpare not:</hi> If this were your Caſe, you would judge a Neceſſity is laid upon <hi>me</hi> to ſpeak plainly, and upon <hi>you</hi> to receive the Word with meekneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt then,</hi> Submit to Chriſt's Scepter as Chriſtians and Men; <hi>Serve the Lord with fear:</hi> How can it be expected that you will to any purpoſe ſubmit to Chriſt as Magiſtrates for the Good of others, if you do not ſubmit to him as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans for the Good of your own Souls? In the Ceremonial Law the Snuffers were of pure Gold, to ſhew the Neceſſity of Holineſs in them that are to be Cenſurers and Correctors of others: Your Stile and Titles ſhew as much; you are call'd God's, and ſhould you be ungodly, you would make Men think, that you are ſuch God's as the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> ſaw riſing out of the Earth, which indeed were Devils: If you live in Rebellion againſt the King of Heaven, you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour your great Maſter, ſtain your Commiſſion, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able your Selves from puniſhing others. For how unſeemly would it be for Vice to correct Sin? And if Vice would be ſo officious, yet <hi>how will you pluck the Mote out of your Brothers Eye, while a Beam is in your own?</hi> And beſides it would give the People juſt reaſon to Lament over you with that of the Prophet, <hi>Our Silver is become droſs,</hi> &amp;c. If you ſhall ask me now what I call Holineſs? I anſwer, 1. Humility, Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encious walking with God, Self-denial, Prayer, hearing the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101413:16"/>Word, Self-examination, Family-worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Works of Piety. 2. The Works of the Fleſh are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, Swearing, Drunkenneſs, Uncleanneſs, Pride, Hatred, Sabbath breaking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are certainly not Holineſs. 3. To live careleſly (though in the Practice of external Duties) after the rate of moſt Men, without Conviction of Sin, Repentance, inward Communion with God, Love, Joy, and delight in his Ways; not ſtriving againſt little Sins, nor watching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vain Thoughts: This is in no other Senſe holineſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, but as a dead Carkaſs is call'd a Man. 4. To think any Service enough for God, ſecretly to loath and hate the Strictneſs of God's Ways, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> will ſhew that you are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Servants to Chriſt who hath requir'd all theſe things of you: Can you deny, but that theſe are the Plain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God? Or, will any Man ſay that Great Men are not bound to theſe things? Be not deceived, <hi>God is not to be mocked,</hi> Gal. 6.7.</p>
            <p>If you'l ſay, That Men that pretend to theſe things are but proud Hypocrites: I anſwer, I will ask no ſtronger Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt you, than what may be drawn from hence. The Objection ſhews, and grants the Neceſſity and the Truth of the Thing I plead for: If others are Hypocrites, where is the Fault? Not in doing theſe Things, for they are expreſly commanded; but in doing them no better, firſt then come up to theſe Things that others do, and then go beyond them in ſincerity of Performance. I pray Scorn not theſe Truths, the Great Judge is at the Door.</p>
            <p>My Second advice to you is, that you oppoſe not Chriſt's Kingdom. Now this may be done two Ways. 1. By ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing his Deſigns in the Means he appoints to propagate it; the preaching of the Word is his <hi>Scepter,</hi> his <hi>Sword,</hi> his <hi>Chariot of Salvation, the Word of the Kingdom,</hi> &amp;c. it is op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed too by diſcountenancing the Work of his Kingdom, the Practice of his Laws, theſe are the King's high Way, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101413:16"/>the Royal Law by the Apoſtle <hi>James.</hi> Now Chriſt's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign is obſtructed: 1. When Men call for Darkneſs and puts out the Light. 2. When they bind heavy Burthers and lay them upon the Shoulders of the Miniſters. 3. When they forbid them the plain and conſcientious Exerciſe of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſaying, <hi>Propheſy to us ſmooth things.</hi> 4. When they take the advantage of their conſcientious Diſſatisfactions, to ſtop the Courſe of their Miniſtry, <hi>laying a Snare on Mizpah, and ſpreading a Net on Tabor.</hi> If you ſhould do thus, The Lord grant he take you not at your Words. See how he threatens this Oppoſition, Hoſ. 5.1. <hi>Hear ye this O Prieſts, and heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en ye houſe of Iſrael! And give ye ear O houſe of the King, for Judgment is toward you, becauſe ye have been a ſnare on Miz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pah, and a net ſpread upon Tabor,</hi> &amp;c. And in Iſa. 30.10, 13. <hi>They ſay to the Seers, See not, and to the Prophets, Propheſy not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Therefore this iniquity ſhall be to you as a breach ready to fall, ſwelling out in a high wall, whoſe breaking cometh ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly at an inſtant.</hi> Conſider alſo how ſuitable the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to ſuch a Sin, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.7, 8. They had laid Snares for the Lord's Prophets, and he puniſheth this iniquity by give<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them Prophets that ſhould be Snares to them: <hi>The days of Viſitation and Recompence are come, Iſrael</hi> ſhall know it even by this, <hi>He will give them Fools for their Prophets, and Madmen for their Teachers.</hi> —It follows, <hi>the Watchman of</hi> Ephraim <hi>was with my God,</hi> that is, as ſome expound it, they never let him alone till he dy'd, and then he had reſt; or as others think, he was with God in earneſt Prayers and Groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: They put him to complain, Well! How doth God avenge himſelf? Even thus: <hi>They ſhall have Prophets that ſhall be a Snare of a Fowler in all their Ways, to blind and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude them, till they bring on God's hatred and Judgment upon them all.</hi> So alſo Mic. 2.11. <hi>He that will Propheſy of Wine and ſtrong Drink, he ſhall even be the Prophet of this People. Again,</hi> The Work of Chriſt's Kingdom is diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101413:17"/>when God's People are abus'd, revil'd, ſcorn'd, and hated for Holineſs, for Praying, Hearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or when they are reſtrain'd from, or interrupted in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Religion, if you do thus, they will cry to their God, or (to ſpeak in the Language of Children) they will go tell their Father, and when he examines the Matter, you will be found fighters againſt God, and he will undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly deliver them out of your Hand, he hath aſſured us of it, Pſal. 12.5. <hi>For the oppreſſion of the Poor, for the ſighing of the Needy, now will I ariſe ſaith the Lord, I will ſet him in ſafety from him that puffeth at him.</hi> Take heed therefore what you do, and give not any Occaſion for Men to read that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.3. backward, ſaying, <hi>Ruler's are not a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to evil works, but to the good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Set your ſelves ſtrenuouſly againſt the Works and Kingdom of the Devil; you have good Laws, which are as Banks againſt the Floods of Ungodlineſs, look well to the Execution of them: Wickedneſs is Fruitful, it needs no planting nor watering, it grows like Hemlock in the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of the Field; all that the Devil will ask of you is but to let him alone; all that wicked Men long for is, that the Yoke may be taken off, that they may go to Hell with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controul: See how the Land breaks forth Impieties, like the Frogs of <hi>Egypt</hi> make the Land to ſtink; Judge of the Nation by this one County, in this little time of <hi>Solſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium,</hi> in the Change of Juſtices, Wickedneſs that was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reſtraint (for Sin is cowardly) is now become a ſtaring, daring Cockatrice: What Sabbath Breakings, and Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſs have we had of late? I impute not this to any in Authority, look but into the Tempers of debauch'd Wretches, and you'l find that their hopes of Licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is the ground of their Love to any Change of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, and the fear of Reſtraint, the ground of their Diſlike: When the King came in, then
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101413:17"/>ſome rejoyc'd that now they might Drink and Swear with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the fear of the Stocks; ſome of you that hear me know the Truth of this; but when he publiſh'd his ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Declaration againſt Debauchery, then as much as they were for the King before, they could ſpeak againſt him, as being a <hi>Puritan</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian:</hi> Theſe have been the Words of ſome; and indeed what better can you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from thoſe that know no other joy but Drunkenneſs and Exceſs? That can delight in no Thank-offering, but ſuch as is fit to be given to ſome drunken God, that can make no better uſe of the King's Name, but ſuch as a Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier makes of his Drenching-horn, to force Drink down their Throats, beyond the Meaſure and Deſires of their own Stomachs? Riſe up then in the Strength and Might of the Lord againſt theſe Impieties: Break the Jaws and Teeth of Wickedneſs, ſpare none of <hi>Amalek,</hi> great nor ſmall; if you do (however privately it may be) <hi>the bleating of the Sheep, and lowing of the Oxen</hi> will diſcover you to be no Friends to Chriſt's Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Make not your Power ſubſervient to your Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Deſires of Revenge, this is not to do Chriſt's Work, but to ſerve your own Turn of him: Remember not former Provocations, and when you come to Puniſh any that formerly have Offended you, put no more into the Scale of Juſtice, then the preſent Crime requires, this is a ſeaſonable Advice, though hard and difficult to Fleſh and Blood, — <hi>Manet altâ mente repoſtum,</hi> &amp;c. to this Purpoſe I might apply a Story which we have of <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> who coming into a School, asked what Art they profeſs'd? They told him the Art of Memory; He reply'd, that the Art of Memory was but an unprofitable Art, and that he had rather learn the Art of Forgetfulneſs: To forget Things that might provoke our Fury and Paſſion, is certainly a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Art, and the beſt way to attain it, in reference to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101413:18"/>what I now put you in mind of, is not only to have the Act of Indemnity and Oblivion <hi>ad unquem,</hi> if I may ſo ſpeak, but to learn it <hi>by Heart:</hi> Let not Law and publick Juſtice be made a Pretence for ſecret Grudges and private Revenge, for this is what the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> calls, Pſal. 58.2. <hi>To weigh out the violence of your hands;</hi> let not Men ſay of you, as <hi>Theodorus Gadareus, Nero</hi>'s Tutor ſaid of him, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that you are Dirt kned with Blood: Will not the wrong'd cry out, <hi>the beſt of them is as a bryar, the moſt upright is ſharper than a thorn hedge,</hi> Mic. 7.4. Read Pſal. 94.20. <hi>Shall the throne of Iniquity have fellowſhip with thee which frameth miſchief by by a law:</hi> See what the Prophet threatens in this Caſe, Iſa. 10.1. <hi>Wo unto them that decree unrighteous decrees, and that write grievouſneſs which they have preſcrib'd, to turn aſide the needy from Judgment,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> In your Adminiſtrations of Juſtice, let there be a decorum and ſuitableneſs both to the Cauſe and to the Perſon: 1. to the Perſon, let Juſtice run with an even Current, without partiality or reſpect of Perſons: It was an old Complaint,
<q>Dat veniam corvis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—</q> and an Ancient Similie wherein Laws were compar'd to Cobwebs, which take the little Flies, but not the Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets: <hi>Levi</hi>'s impartiality, even to the diſowning of nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Relations when God requir'd it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.9. is your Pattern. 2. Let there be a ſuitableneſs to the Cauſe, as that varieth, ſo muſt you let out ſeverity or clemency, activity or moderation. To Puniſh ſmaller Tranſgreſſions with the ſame Scorpions that you would Puniſh greater withal, can never be juſtifi'd by ſuch a Heterodox Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox as that of <hi>Cicero,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all Sins are equal: To have Life and Activity about the <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Aniſe,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:101413:18"/>wholly neglecting the <hi>greater Things of the Law,</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Mouth of Chriſt himſelf; as Juſtice muſt be your Robe and Diadem, ſo that Robe though wrought of divers Colours, muſt carry an equal ſuitableneſs of Embroidery, and not like a Beggar's Cloak (pardon the Compariſon) one Piece good Cloth and another Courſe: The Scales of Juſtice muſt not have a falſe Ballance, or a Bag of deceitful Weights.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Let Chriſt be the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of all your Employments, carry him along with you in your Heart, ſet him before your Eyes, make him your Pattern, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult with him as your Oracle and Lawgiver, let him be the Loadſtone to your Souls to draw them to him, for the Ends of his Glory; truly you'l have little Comfort in any thing you do, if you as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaid of <hi>Tully</hi>'s Work's, find not the Name of Chriſt in it, <hi>for of him, and to him, and thro' him are all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with my Directions, I ſhould now preſs this upon you, but I ſhall uſe no other Motive, than that of the Text, you muſt do this upon Pain of his Diſpleaſure, <hi>Kiſs the Son leaſt he be angry:</hi> After a few days are paſs'd over your Head, you muſt give up your Account to him, who is the Righteous Judge, who will not be afraid of your Looks, nor regard your Perſons more then the Meaneſt, but will render to you accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your ways and doings: If you be Guilty, you will tremble a Thouſand-fold more before his Throne, then the Guilty Criminals ſhall tremble before yours this Day; if it be found, that while you were in the Throne you oppreſs'd his Kingdom, he will then make you his Footſtool, and then Ten thouſand times Wo to you, you had better never have known your Honours and Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; you will then find that any Trouble or Moleſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion caus'd by you on the Innocent or Pious, ſhall be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vier
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101413:19"/>on you that inflicted it, than for thoſe that ſuffer'd by you: When they ſhall be comforted, and you tormented, <hi>Sol Juſtitiae qui quondam erat in ſigno leonis, nunc in ſigno vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis, tunc erit in ſigno librae,</hi> as <hi>Abſſabritius</hi> hath it. His meaning is, that God will weigh you in a ſtrict Ballance, and he can eaſily do it if he be angry never ſo little, by the Breath of his Mouth they Periſh, as eaſily as a <hi>Bear can tear the Caul of a Man's Heart,</hi> Hoſ. 13.8. <hi>O that you would conſider this, and be inſtructed ye Judges of the earth;</hi> take Advice in time, advance the Honour of Chriſt, and of his Ways in your ſelves and others, and then he will Crown you with Glory and Immortality, <hi>for bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I diſmiſs you, I ſhall ſpeak a word or two to the People.</p>
            <p>You have heard how Plain I have been with the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and I know People love to hear them ſo dealt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and yet the Lord knows I have not done it to make you Sport: Their Ingenuity and Religion will make them take it well: Will you take it as well if I uſe the ſame boldneſs of Speech to you? I have not time to preſs much upon you, I ſhall only charge you with theſe <hi>Four</hi> Things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Do you alſo kiſs the Son. If Magiſtrates muſt do ſo, much more you, and this is one Reaſon why Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates are only mention'd in the Exhortation of the <hi>Pſalm,</hi> if their Greatneſs cannot excuſe them, what can you plead for an exemption from this Duty? Do not then oppoſe Chriſt's Kingdom, by your own Diſobedience and Contempt of his Commands, break off your Sins by Repentance, be at laſt aſham'd of Swearing, Drunkenneſs, Uncleanneſs, Sabbath-breaking, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> neither do you Reproach others for taking more Care of their Souls, than you are willing to take of your own: Make Conſcience of Family-worſhip, attend on Preaching, examine the Condition of your Hearts,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101413:19"/>and be Examples of Piety to others: For this purpoſe I ſhall mention two Incouragements to you; 1. Thus will Chriſt be a hiding Place and Sanctuary for you, and your Avenger: If Magiſtrates ſhould become as <hi>evening Wolves,</hi> yet God would awake for you; it is the Concluſion of <hi>Pſalm</hi> 58. which was penn'd for a Support againſt wicked Ruler's, that God would ſo viſibly ſtand up for his People, that a Man ſhould ſay, <hi>Verily there is a reward for the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, verily he is a God that Judgeth in the earth.</hi> And Luke 18.8. <hi>Shall not God avenge his own elect, that cry night and day, I tell you he will avenge them ſpeedily.</hi> 2. A ſecond En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement is, that thus may God make your Ruler's Good, and give them as a Bleſſing; the Reaſon why <hi>Saul</hi> was ſuch an Oppreſſive Ruler, was from the Sin's of the People, that provoked God to give them a King in his Wrath: The Reaſon of <hi>David</hi>'s miſcarriage in numbring the People, was the People's Sin that provoked God in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to <hi>Iſrael</hi> to permit his Fall, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.1. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. In the Body Natural, the deſtillations from the Head up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Stomach, are uſually from the Stomach firſt, which afflicts the Head before the Head trouble it; ſo in the Body Politick, our Sin's provoke God to, leave our Ruler's to Temptation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let me charge you, That if Magiſtrates are ſo much intruſted with Chriſt's Kingdom, you neglect not to Pray for them, you have very great Reaſons to induce you to it, and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. gives theſe three Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that ſhould ſtir you up to this Duty even to wicked Ruler's; 1. Our own Benefit, Encouragement, and Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Ways of Religion, v. 2. <hi>That we may lead a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſs and honeſty.</hi> 2. A ſecond Reaſon for it is, the Acce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>leneſs of it to God, v. 3. <hi>This is good and acceptable in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght of God our Saviour.</hi> And 3. He endeavours to perſwade Men to this Duty, from the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101413:20"/>poſſibility of the Change of their Hearts, v. 4. <hi>In that God would have all Men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If then the Magiſtrates are God's Truſtees, and Inſtruments, then for Conſcience ſake let them have Reſpect in our Carriage and Language according to their Places: <hi>Paul</hi> acknowledg'd his Failing in this, <hi>Acts</hi> 23.5. when he call'd the high Prieſt <hi>whited Wall,</hi> the Expoſitions uſually given here, are either <hi>groſs,</hi> as if <hi>Paul</hi> meant his Wickedneſs had brought a Forfeiture of his Honour upon him, and ſo he would not acknowledge him as high Prieſt; or <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory,</hi> as if <hi>Paul</hi> who was no Stranger in <hi>Iſrael</hi> did not know the Perſon of the high Prieſt, and yet acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a Judge, <hi>ſitteſt thou to Judge,</hi> &amp;c. ſo that if you will pardon me in a little ſingularity, I would thus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>non conſiderabam:</hi> I conſider'd not; and thus you find, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> tranſlated (as it cannot properly be otherwiſe) <hi>Conſiderans,</hi> Conſidering, or when he had conſidered: So that <hi>Paul</hi> here acknowledgeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitancy, and eats his Words as not warrantable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Obey the Magiſtrates, and ſubmit actively in all lawful Things, and paſſively, when it comes to thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you muſt obey God rather than Man.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101413:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
